Guide to the William A. Price Papers TAM.398
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
William A. Price Papers
1930-2009
1960-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Tenants Association/Mutual Housing Association-Housing Development Fund Corporation, Inc. (UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc.)
Price, William Addison, 1915-2009
United Tenants Association. Ad Hoc Committee for Low-Rent Housing
Price, Elizabeth
Albano, Lou
TAM.398
21.25 Linear Feet in 20 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 small flat box
William Addison Price (1915-2009) was a journalist and community organizer. He worked for the New York Daily News as a United Nations correspondent and later wrote about social issues in New York City and the civil rights movement in the South for the National Guardian. In 1956, Price invoked his First Amendment rights when called before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee, which was investigating allegations of Communist infiltration in the media. Price began working with the United Tenants Association (UTA) and other housing rights organizations in the 1970s, fighting the New York City government's plans to develop the Upper West Side. The collection is mostly comprised of materials generated by the UTA and other housing rights groups, as well as the New York City government, regarding urban renewal plans in the designated West Side Urban Renewal Area (WSURA). There are also materials related to the civil rights movement, the opposition to the House Un-American Activities Committee and other Congressional inquisitorial groups, and the state of journalism and journalists' unions. The collection also contains biographical information on Price, particularly his World War II service.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of Box 10, Box 14, and Box 15. Repository permission is required for access to Box 10, Box 14, and Box 15. Please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, 212-998-2630.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Elizabeth Price sent two donations of William A. Price's papers in 2007 and 2009. In 2011, Hope DeRogatis sent an additional eight boxes of William Price's files on West Side Housing and West Side Urban Renewal. Louis Albano sent an additional gift of five of Price's journals from Fire Island House in 2012. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2007.018, 2009.064, 2011.094, and 2012.078.
Arrangement
This collection is unprocessed. Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical/Biographical Note
William Addison Price (1915-2009) was a journalist and community organizer. He grew up in Montclair, NJ and flew air-rescue missions for the Navy during World War II, earning the rank of lieutenant. Price's war experiences inspired him to become a socialist. He joined the New York Daily News in 1940, eventually becoming the paper's United Nations correspondent. In 1948, Price and other members of the Newspaper Guild founded the Newsmen's Committee to Investigate the Murder of George Polk, who was Price's cousin and a fellow journalist. (Polk was murdered in Greece during the Greek civil war by forces allied with the anti-communist government.)
Price appeared before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee, an inquisitorial committee which was investigating allegations that Communists had infiltrated the media, in 1956. The Subcommittee inquired if Price was a member of the Communist Party and if he used the plane he owned as a courier aircraft for the Communist International. Price invoked the First Amendment, rather than the Fifth, and argued that the Subcommittee did not have the right to inquire into his political beliefs. He was fired from the Daily News after testifying before the Subcommittee, and additionally was found guilty of contempt of Congress and was fined and imprisoned. Price's appearance before the inquisitorial committee and its aftermath spurred him to become a participant in the Committee of First Amendment Defendants coordinating committee. He also served as secretary of the New York Council to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee.
Price later wrote for the National Guardian, covering social issues in New York City and the civil rights movement in the South. In 1981, Price was awarded $10,000 by the Department of Justice after the FBI's "Squad 47" was found to have illegally wiretapped Price and four others on suspicion that they were associated with the Weather Underground. During the 1980s and 1990s, Price was a member and periodic resident of a congregate living house on Fire Island.
Beginning in the 1970s and continuing into the 2000s, Price worked with a number of community organizations on New York City's Upper West Side to defend tenants' rights and protest the city's urban renewal plans. He was particularly active with the United Tenants Association (UTA), an organization of tenants who lived in buildings in the city's designated West Side Urban Renewal Area (WSURA), and was treasurer of the later dissident subgroup of UTA, the Ad Hoc Committee for Low-Rent Housing. Founded in 1977 by the mostly low-income inhabitants of several city-owned buildings, UTA fought for the right to manage and rehabilitate the buildings in which its members lived, fearing that development in the WSURA would raise rents and push minority groups out of the area. The city's Fifth Amendment to the WSURA plan was passed by the early 1980s and guaranteed UTA tenants the right to rehabilitate the buildings they inhabited as low-rent apartments. However, it was not until 1991 that UTA began renovating the buildings through the city's Mutual Housing Association program (run by the Department of Housing Preservation and Development), thereby forming the United Tenants Association/Mutual Housing Association-Housing Development Fund Corporation, Inc. (UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc.). Members of UTA's Ad Hoc Committee contended that UTA's association with the Mutual Housing Association would cause rents to continually increase and cause further gentrification of the area, as many low-income families in the area had already been relocated by urban renewal. In addition to the dispute between UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. and UTA Ad Hoc, UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. also brought nonpayment proceedings against Price and other tenants who refused to pay the increased interim rents.
Related Archival Materials at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Researchers interested in tenants' associations on the Upper West Side may wish to consult the Park West Village Tenants Association Records (TAM 333) and the Westgate Tenants Association Records (TAM 521).
Other collections related to housing rights in New York City include:
Metropolitan Council on Housing Records (TAM 173)
Bernard Goodman Tenants' Activism and Miscellaneous Papers (TAM 201)
John Penley Photographs and Papers (TAM 501)
Ronald Lawson: Tenant Movement in New York City Research Files (TAM 214)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Fly Papers (TAM 363)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Jane Churchman Papers (TAM 313)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Jerry "The Peddler" Wade (TAM 366)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Kurt Reynertson Papers (TAM 335)
Squatters' Rights Collection: On Davis Papers (TAM 365)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Peter Spagnuolo Papers (TAM 336)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Roland Politi Papers (TAM 364)
Tamiment Library's Housing Web Archive
Researchers interested in opposition movements against HUAC may wish to consult the New York Council to Abolish HUAC Records (TAM 431) and the Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM 132).
Researchers interested in the Newspaper Guild may wish to consult the Newspaper Guild Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 002), the Newspaper Guild of New York Records (WAG 125), and the Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk Records (TAM 159).
Researchers interested in the civil rights movement may wish to consult James E. Jackson and Esther Cooper Jackson Papers (TAM 347), the Southern Negro Youth Congress: FBI Files (TAM 265), and numerous other collections at the Tamiment Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection, which spans from the 1930s to the 2000s but dates mostly from the 1960s through 1990s, is a rich source of information for researchers interested in tenants' rights in New York City's Upper West Side. The collection is predominately comprised of agendas and minutes; proposals and reports; legal documents; correspondence and memoranda; press releases; news clippings; and flyers, pamphlets, and other printed ephemera related to the debates over the development of the city's designated West Side Urban Renewal Area (WSURA). Most of the materials were generated by the United Tenants Association (UTA), later known as the United Tenants Association/Mutual Housing Authority-Housing Development Fund Corporation, Inc. (UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc.). The materials document UTA's protests to the city's urban renewal plans for the WSURA and its promotion of the construction of low-income housing. The collection also reflects the internal politics of UTA, particularly the dispute between UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. and UTA's Ad Hoc Committee for Low-Rent Housing and UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. against Price. Government entities represented in the collection, which UTA and other community groups frequently interacted with, include Community Board #7, the NYC Department of Housing Preservation and Development (HPD), and HPD's Division of Alternative Management Programs (DAMP). The activities of other community groups with an interest in the development of the Upper West Side are also documented, including (but not limited to) the Strycker's Bay Neighborhood Council, the Community Service Society of New York, the Metropolitan Council on Housing, the 87th Street West Park Association, the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB), and Community Action, Inc. (particularly Operation Move-In). There are also materials generated by the Committee of Neighbors to Insure a Normal Urban Environment (CONTINUE), which, in contrast to most other community group included in the collection, opposed the construction of subsidized housing.
The collection also speaks to the political environment of the mid-20th century, particularly the civil rights movement and the resistance to anti-Communist investigations. Newsletters, flyers, reports, news clippings, correspondence, and other materials pertaining to the civil rights movement were collected by Price through his coverage of the movement as a journalist and his personal involvement in the cause. Many of these materials were generated by the Southern Conference Educational Fund (SCEF), as well as the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee and other activist groups. Two boxes of reel-to-reel recording tapes appear to be mostly of civil rights meetings and events. A significant amount of the collection pertains to activism against the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) and other Congressional inquisitorial committees in the form of memoranda and correspondence, flyers, governing documents, press releases, newsletters, and other materials, many created by the National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee (NCAHUAC) or the group's local New York Council to Abolish HUAC. In a similar vein, there are subject files on First Amendment cases compiled by the Committee of First Amendment Defendants (CFDA).
To a much lesser extent, the collection includes clippings and correspondence that provide biographical information on Price. Especially noteworthy is Price's family correspondence from World War II, when Price served as a Navy pilot. Materials created by the Communist Party, both national and New York branches, and the Independent-Socialist Party reflect Price's political affiliations. The collection also serves as a resource for researchers interested in the organization and activism of newspaper unions and offices, as it contains correspondence and other materials from the Newspaper Guild, the Guild's Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk, and the National Guardian. A small amount of material relates to Price's time on Fire Island (including the journals he kept while living there) and the "Squad 47" wiretapping case.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Some materials in boxes 2, 7, 8, 11, 12, 13, 17, 18, 20, and 22 are especially fragile and should be handled with care.
Box 10 was isolated due to suspected mold growth and is currently closed to researchers. Boxes 14 and 15, which contain reel-to-reel tapes in poor condition, are also closed.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
Runs of City Star and other publications were separated for library cataloging. An oversize photograph from Box 2 was separated to Box OS004, which is indicated in the collection with a removal slip.
Unannotated duplicates of printed ephemera created in bulk were sampled and the remainder discarded. A run of the National Guardian from 1966-1967 was removed from the collection. Individual bank statements and checks were also discarded.
Socialism -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Community organization -- New York (State) -- New York; Journalists -- United States.; Discrimination in housing.; Housing -- New York (State) -- New York; Landlord and tenant -- New York (State) -- New York; Anti-communist movements -- United States.; Civil rights -- United States.; Tenants' associations -- New York (State) -- New York.; West Side (New York, N.Y.); United Tenants Association/Mutual Housing Association-Housing Development Fund Corporation, Inc. (UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc.); New York (City). Department of Housing Preservation and Development (HPD); Independent-Socialist Party (U.S.); Southern Conference Educational Fund; Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (New York, N.Y.); Communist Party of the United States of America; Community Service Society of New York; Polk, George, 1913-1948; Strycker's Bay Neighborhood Council; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee; Committee of Neighbors to Insure a Normal Urban Environment (CONTINUE); Committee of First Amendment Defendants; Price, William Addison, 1915-2009; United Tenants Association. Ad Hoc Committee for Low-Rent Housing; Price, Elizabeth; Albano, Lou
- Box 1, 1930s-1990s
  Scope and Content Note
  This box mainly contains Price's correspondence with family and friends. The majority of the correspondence documents Price's World War II service, though many of the letters were written later and pertain to both his personal life and his various activism interests. Correspondents include Price's parents, his nephew George Jefferson Price III ("Jeff"), and Judith Gregory. Some of Price's World War II correspondence, along with news clippings and photographs from his service and clippings and publicity materials from the National Conference for New Politics, appear to have been collected by Price for a scrapbook.
  This box also contains materials related to Price's journalism career, including reports and memoranda on changes at the National Guardian and reports, correspondence, newsletters, and news clippings related to the work of the Newspaper Guild's Anti-Discrimination Committee.
  Evidence of Price's activism in opposition to the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) is also present in the form of news clippings on an April 1961 rally to abolish HUAC and memoranda, minutes, petitions, newsletters, press releases, and notes created by the National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee (NCAHUAC) and its local New York Council. Some of the materials document the fraught relationship between the national and New York groups.
  To a much lesser extent, the box contains campaign material promoting the Progressive Party and Henry A. Wallace's 1948 run for president; First Amendment subject files on Arthur Miller and Otto Nathan containing news clippings, correspondence, and photographs; newsletters, correspondence, and reports produced by the American Veterans Committee (AVC), including a report written by Price for AVC titled "The Negro Doctor in Montclair and His Relationship to Montclair Hospitals;" documentation from a civil suit between Price and his siblings against their sister, Harriet Price; and correspondence and other material related to a family reunion Price helped organize in Oxford, New Jersey.
- Box 2, 1940s-2000s
  About half of the materials in this box relate to housing rights issues. The materials document the work of the United Tenants Association (UTA), later the UTA/Mutual Housing Association-Housing Development Fund Corporation (UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc.), and other housing rights organizations during the 1970s through 1980s in the form of UTA Steering Committee minutes and UTA proposals, memoranda and correspondence, official statements, reports, and publicity materials, as well as collected news clippings. Many of the materials relate to the development plans for the West Side Urban Renewal Area (WSURA), particularly the UTA and the Strycker's Bay Neighborhood Council's interactions with Community Board #7 and the NYC Department of Housing Preservation and Development (HPD) regarding WSURA. There is also material generated by the UTA Ad Hoc Committee for Low-Rent Housing, which documents the Ad Hoc Committee's opposition to the UTA/MHA program and the dispute between the Ad Hoc Committee and UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. Correspondence, legal documents, and other materials from the 1990s provide evidence of Price's dispute regarding the rehabilitation of his apartment under the Mutual Housing Association Program (MHAP).
  The other half of the box contains Price's correspondence and notes from Fire Island; legal documents and correspondence with lawyer Harry Rand and others regarding the U.S. v. Price First Amendment case; legal documents, photographs, and news clippings from the Price v. Kearney "Squad 47" wire tapping case; publicity materials, news clippings, and correspondence and memoranda documenting the activities of the New York Council to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee; what appear to be school notes; a brief working manuscript of Price's memoir written at age 60 and parts of his diary from 1940; subject files on the political climate in Israel, Egypt, Greece (including documents created by the American Committee for Democracy and Freedom in Greece), and Cuba (including a proposal for a photographers' trip to Cuba); and a miscellaneous assortment of correspondence, photographs, and news clippings relating to Price's personal life and various left-wing causes.
- Box 3, 1940s-1990s
  The majority of materials in this box relate to the UTA and the UTA Ad Hoc Committee for Low-Rent Housing and their relationship to HPD, Community Board #7, and the NYC Housing Authority. There is also a small amount of material generated by the Committee of Neighbors to Insure a Normal Urban Environment (CONTINUE), the Strycker's Bay Neighborhood Council (SBNC), the Community Service Society of New York, and other community organizations. The materials in the box include memoranda and correspondence, agendas and minutes, budgets, reports and proposals, legal and government documents, by-laws, newsletters, news clippings, and flyers and other publicity materials. Topics covered include the Fifth Amendment to the WSURA Plan, the origins of UTA, squatters rights, the UTA/MHA proposal, the status of individual buildings, NYC In Rem housing, Mutual Housing Associations, community land trusts, the non-payment cases brought against UTA Ad Hoc Committee members, and the general struggle to construct low-rent public housing in the Upper West Side.
- Box 4, 1960s-1990s
  This box is mostly comprised of materials related to the housing rights struggle in the Upper West Side, particularly the status of several specific building sites. The box includes materials generated by the UTA, UTA Ad Hoc Committee, the SBNC, the Metropolitan Council on Housing, the Coalition for Replanning the West Side Urban Renewal Area, Coummunity Board #7, HPD, the 87th Street West Park Association, and other organizations. Materials include agendas and minutes, proposals and reports, flyers, news clippings, newsletters, legal and government documents, and correspondence and memoranda. To a lesser extent, this box also documents other topics like the the UTA/MHA proposal, the Senior Citizen Rent Increase Exemption program, rent collection, WSURA relocation (including documents created by the Citizens' Relocation Advisory Board), and the overall development of the WSURA. There are several photographs of a 1980 UTA demonstration and buildings in the WSURA.
  Additionally, this box contains a paper on racism against Africa and African Americans, Price's personal correspondence, and news clippings, government documents, and materials generated by various antiwar and/or civil liberties groups (including NCAHUAC) related to the HUAC anti-Vietnam War hearings held in August 1966.
- Box 5, 1960s-1990s
  This box is mostly comprised of materials related to the status of several specific building sites in the WSURA and the activities of Operation Move-In (part of Community Action, Inc.) in regards to the WSURA. These materials, created and collected by the UTA and Operation Move-In, consist of agendas and minutes, correspondence and memoranda, news clippings, newsletters, notes, flyers and other publicity materials, reports and proposals (including those created by the Mid-West Side Community Corporation), government documents, and official statements.
  Additionally, the box contains materials on the topic of racism, namely conference materials and articles, papers, and reports, apparently gathered and in some cases written by an organization called People Against Racism (PAR). There is also a small subject file on the Mariana Islands and a significant number of legal documents pertaining to the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. vs. Price case.
- Box 6, 1950s-2000s
  This box is mainly comprised of legal documents pertaining to the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. vs. Price, UTA/MHA vs. UTA Ad Hoc, and various other civil cases involving Price and/or the UTA.
  The box also contains a general assortment of news articles (some written by Price), notes, press releases, reports, and other materials, some prepared by various NYC housing groups. These materials generally pertain to housing and preservation issues in NYC, particularly urban dislocation, racism in city planning, and the Fifth Amendment to the West Side Urban Renewal Plan. Other topics documented include civil rights, poverty, Cuba, labor history, and HUAC. There is also some personal correspondence and a number of unidentified photographs and negatives, as well as slides and notes prepared for a slideshow on the "Architecture of Fear."
- Box 7, 1940s-2000s